<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" id="chapter.getting-started">
	<title>Getting Started</title>
	<para>
		Phake depends on PHP 5.2.4 or greater. It has no dependency on PHPUnit and should be usable with
		any version of PHPUnit so long as the PHP version is 5.2.4 or greater.
	</para>
	<para>
		Phake can be installed via the digitalsandwich pear channel. This channel is located at
		<link xlink:href="http://pear.digitalsandwich.com">pear.digitalsandwich.com</link>.
	</para>
	<xi:include href="getting-started/pear.xml" />
	<para>
		Once Phake is installed, so long as the pear directory (usually something like /usr/share/php) is 
		in your include_path, you can simply include “Phake.php” in your code and you will be able to utilize
		the functionality of Phake.
	</para>
	<para>
		For those that you like to live more on the edge, you can also clone a copy of Phake from the Phake 
		GitHub repository at <link xlink:href="http://github.com/mlively/Phake">git://github.com/mlively/Phake.git</link>.
		Every attempt is made to keep the master branch stable and this should be usable for those that
		immediately need features before they get released or in the event that you enjoy the bleeding edge.
		Always remember, until something goes into a rc state, there is always a chance that the functionality
		may change. However as an early adopter that uses GitHub, you can have a chance to mold the software
		as it is built.
	</para>
    <section>
        <title>Support</title>
        <para>
            If you think you have found a bug or an issue with Phake, please feel free to open up an issue on the
            github issue tracker: <link xlink:href="http://github.com/mlively/Phake/issues" />.
        </para>
        <para>
            If you have questions about Phake, you can email the phake google group:
            <link xlink:href="http://groups.google.com/group/phake-users" />
        </para>
        <para>
            You can also email me directly at m@digitalsandwich.com or get a hold of me on various channels on the
            freenode irc network (mlively or mlively-work) though I cannot guarantee quick responses through these two
            methods.
        </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
